George J. Dufek Papers
George J. Dufek Papers
1946-1971
Dufek, George J. (George John), 1903-
9 linear ft.
The career of Admiral George John Dufek (1903-1977) in the U.S. Navy included work with the U.S. Antarctic Service (1939-1941), Arctic Task Force 68 (1946), Antarctic Operation Highjump (1946-1947) and Arctic Task Force 80 (1948). After 1955 Dufek commanded Operation Deep Freeze, which provided support for US IGY research programs, and in 1956 he became also U.S. Antarctic Projects Officer. After retiring in 1959 he became Director of the Mariners' Museum in Virginia. Cf. Peter J. Beck, Polar Record, v. 23, no. 145 (1987). The collection includes clippings, photographs, official reports, draft speeches, personal and official correspondence, articles, and scrapbooks. Files relating to Operation Deep Freeze include chronologies, record books, reports, photographs and scrapbooks. There is also some material relating to Dufek's other Arctic and Antarctic expeditions, however these operations are less fully documented.
149335
Biographical History
George John Dufek (1903-1977) was an American naval officer and arctic expert. Born in Rockford, Illinois, he joined the Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC) at his local high school and was appointed to the U.S. Naval Academy in Annapolis, Maryland in 1921. Upon graduation in 1925 he received his ensign's commission and commenced his career aboard the battleship USS Maryland. In 1932 he entered flight training school at the U.S. Navy air station in Pensacola, Florida; after graduating as a naval aviator in 1933 he served as navigator and executive officer on three different ships
By 1939 Dufek had been promoted to lieutenant. That spring he requested and received an assignment with Rear Admiral Richard E. Byrd's third expedition to Antarctica, where he served as navigator of the USS Bear, the flagship of the expedition. In recognition of his many hours of exploratory flying over the South Polar continent Dufek later received the Antarctic Expedition Medal.
During World War II Dufek commanded a flight training squadron, served as senior naval aviator in Algeria during the invasion of North Africa, assisted in the planning for the invasion of Sicily and Salerno and, after his promotion to captain and subsequent reassignment, the invasion of southern France. In September 1944 he assumed command of the USS Bogue, which sank the final German submarine lost in World War II.
After a brief post-war stint in Japan, Dufek was assigned as chief staff officer to a U.S. Navy-Coast Guard task force to establish weather bases in the polar regions. While there he participated in Operation Highjump, a Naval expedition to Antarctica under the command of Admiral Byrd, during which he made the first flight over the Thurston Peninsula and later rescued six survivors of another flight over the same area. He returned to Washington D.C. briefly but by 1947 was back in the Antarctic, this time commanding a task force sent to supply existing weather stations and to establish new ones near the Pole.
During the Korean War the Navy placed Dufek in command of the USS Antietam, then on Kwajalein Island in the Pacific and finally at Whidbey Island Naval air station in Oak Harbor, Washington. But in 1954 his cold-weather expertise was again in demand when he joined a special antarctic planning group preparing for the Navy's Operation Deepfreeze, a scientific polar research expedition. When planning was complete Dufek was given command of Task Force 43, which included more than 80 officers and 1000 enlisted men, three ice-breakers, and three cargo ships, was charged with logistics and support for the expedition. Among other accomplishments the task force established bases on Ross Island and in Little America, and on October 31, 1956 Admiral Dufek and six fellow travelers became the first Americans ever to set foot at the South Pole and to plant the American flag, and the first men ever to land on the pole from the air. After Admiral Byrd's death, Dufek was appointed to succeed him as supervisor of U.S. programs in the South Polar Regions.
Among the numerous recognitions and awards he has received are the Legion of Merit with two Gold Stars, World War II Victory Medal, Korean Service Medal, Croix de Guerre and the Korean Presidential Citation. He is a member of the Legion of Honor with the rank of chevalier, and in August 1957 he received the Distinguished Service Medal.
[Adapted from "Dufek, George J." in Current Biography (1957).]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George J. Dufek Papers are arranged chronologically beginning with his 1938 assignment aboard the U.S.S. Arneb, through his career in the U.S. Navy and appointment as Director of the Mariners' Museum. Dufek's career included work with the U.S. Antarctic Service (1939-1941), Arctic Task Force 68 (1946), Antarctic Operation Highjump (1946-1947), and Arctic Task Force 80 (1948). After 1955 Dufek commanded Operation Deep Freeze, which provided Support for U.S. participation, in International Geophysical Year research programs. Following his retirement in 1959, Dufek became Director of the Mariners' Museum in Virginia. Dufek's papers reflect his interests in both polar regions, and his role in Antarctic affairs between 1955 and 1959. (Cf. "The Papers of Admiral George Dufek ..." by Peter J. Beck from Polar Record, vol. 23, no. 145, 1987.)
The Dufek papers contain chronologies, personal and official correspondence, manuals, reports, press releases, speeches, internal memos, writings, and photographs. The twelve scrapbooks at the end of the collection document the years between 1956 and 1959, with special emphasis an Operation Deep Freeze. They are supplemented by an extensive clippings file which covers 1946 through 1971.
Arrangement of the Collection
Papers are arranged chronologically by major topic and again chronologically within that.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Science and medicine; Dufek, George J. (George John), 1903-; Antietam (Aircraft carrier); United States. -- Navy. -- Task Force 43.; United States. -- Navy. -- Task Force 68.; United States. -- Navy. -- Task Force 66.; United States. -- Navy -- Officers.; Mariners' Museum (Newport News, Va.); Admirals -- United States.; Scientific expeditions -- Antarctica.; Scientific expeditions -- Arctic regions.; Scientific expeditions -- Polar regions.; International Geophysical Year, 1957-1958.; Transportation, Military -- Cold weather conditions -- Research.; Arctic regions.; Antarctica.; Polar regions.; Audiotapes.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Phonograph records.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Admirals.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of George J. Dufek, 1973. Gift of George J. Dufek, Jr., 2013.
Inventory
- Pre-World War II
  - Press release, U.S.S. Arneb, 1938; Feb. 1938 (Box 1)
- World War II
  - Bogue Bulletin, Mar. 1945 (Box 1)
  - Orders, 1945 (Box 1)
- Task Force 68
  - Manuals and reports
    - "Arctic Navigation", Oct. 1947 (Box 1)
    - "Arctic Warfare" bibliographies, June, Oct. 1946 (Box 1)
    - Bibliography on Ice of the Northern Hemisphere, 1945 (Box 1)
    - "Cold and Heavy Weather Operations", Mar. 1946 (Box 1)
    - "Development of Ice-Breaking Vessels for the U.S. Coast Guard," Harvey S. Johnson, "advance copy of paper to be presented at annual meeting, November 14 and 15, 1946" of the Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers (Box 1)
    - "The German Antarctic Expedition of 1938-1939" (Box 1)
    - "Landings on Ice at Cambridge Bay, Canada", June 1947 (Box 1)
    - "Report by U.S. Weather Bureau Observers on Arctic Activities", Summer 1947 (Box 1)
  - Public Information Office
    - Biographical sketches, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Internal memos, July-Aug. 1946 (Box 1)
    - Photographs, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Press interviews, Oct. 1946 (Box 1)
    - Press releases, July-Dec. 1946; undated (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia
    - Operation Nanook photographs, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Operation Nanook leather scrapbook cover (Box 2)
    - "The Secret Land", MGM movie promotional material (Box 2)
- Task Force 80
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Intelligence reports
    - "Geographical Intelligence Report no. 5", undated (Box 2)
    - "The Warming of the Arctic", Jan. 1949; translation of Chapter 7 of N.N. Zubov's In the Center of the Arctic (Box 2)
  - Internal memos, July-Aug. 1948 (Box 2)
  - Manuals and reports
    - "The Arctic", undated (Box 2)
    - "Climatology of Polar Regions", July 1948 (Box 2)
    - Cold weather training manuals, variously titled, 1948; 5 items (Box 2)
    - "Ice Service in Finland", 1937 (Box 2)
    - "Manual of Ice Seamanship", 1948 (Box 2)
    - "Plan for Arctic Test Transportation Corps Equipment", Aug. 1948 (Box 2)
    - "United States Weather Bureau Plans and Instructions for Arctic Operations", summer 1948 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous fragments: "Air bedding bill"; "Flight quarters bill", undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1948; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3)
  - "Ronne Antarctic Research Expedition 1946-1948", article by Finn Ronne (reprinted from The Geographical Review, vol. XXXVIII, no. 3 (Box 3)
  - Writings, miscellaneous, undated; 2 untitled items about U.S. Navy interests in the Arctic and Antarctic and a chronology of Task Force 80 departure; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Joint staff
  - Correspondence
    - Navy, official, 1948-1949 (Box 3)
    - Personal, 1948-1950 (Box 3)
  - Report, "A Study Involving a New Design of Icebreaker", Nov. 14, 1950 (Box 3)
- Task Force 66
  - Preliminary material
    - "Second Staff Study", Dec. 28, 1948 (Box 3)
    - Conference report an Highjump, Planning Group Two, Jan. 12, 1949 (Box 3)
    - "Third Staff Study", Mar. 14, 1949 (Box 3)
    - "Preliminary Statement of Scientific Missions to be Undertaken by the 1950 Navy Antarctic Developments Project (Highjump II) Task Force 66", Aug. 1949 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1949; official Navy correspondence (Box 3)
  - Manual containing procedures for parachuting sled-dogs (Box 3)
  - Report, "Antarctic Research Elements of a Coordinated Program", May 1949 (Box 3)
- U.S.S. Antietam
  - Correspondence
    - Letters of appreciation written to the Captain, 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - Numbered correspondence 1-131, 1951-1952; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Printed material
    - Antietam, vol. 1-2, 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - Memorabilia
    - Photographs of U.S.S. Antietam Guest Cruise, April 26-May 2, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Program for U.S.S. Antietam cruise, Pearl Harbor/San Francisco, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Yearbook, 1951-1952; photo-narrative album (Box 3)
- Naval air bases commander
  - Correspondence, personal, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
  - Dispatches, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Memos, 1952 (Box 4)
- Task Force 43
  - Correspondence, 1955-1959 (Box 4)
  - Dispatches and memos, 1957; 1959 (Box 4)
  - Journals, 1956; 1958 (Box 4)
  - Manuals and reports
    - "Expedicion Argentina al Mar de Weddell", translation from Spanish (Box 4)
    - Selected Maps and Charts of Antarctica, 1959 (Box 4)
    - "Staff Instructions", Aug. 1955 (Box 4)
    - "Seismic Observations of the Bird Station Traverse Party", Feb. 1958 (Box 4)
    - "Traverse Operations on the Ross Ice Shelf", Mar. 1958 (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - Dr. Fuchs' party at the South Pole, Jan. 19-20, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4)
  - Public Information Office press releases, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Miscellany
    - "All Seven Survived" by George Moss, manuscript (Box 7)
    - "Operation Plan no. 1-56," Knox Coast Task Group (Box 7)
    - "Passenger List of 'Bravo Detachment' Personnel Embarked on USS Curtiss" (Box 7)
    - "Receipt for Special Clothing and Gear", Aug. 1956 (Box 7)
- Task Force 43, Operation Deep Freeze
  - Chronology, 1957-1958 (Box 7)
  - Interview transcripts, undated; 3 items (Box 7)
  - Manuals and reports
    - "Operation Plan no. 1-55", 1955; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - "Report of Operation Deep Freeze IV", 1958-1959 (Box 7)
  - Photographs, 1956; undated; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Public Information Office press releases, Apr. 26, 1957 (Box 7)
  - Speech, rough draft outline (Box 7)
  - Writings
    - "Operation Deep Freeze Fits Out", 1955; manuscript by George Dufek with Joseph E. Oglesby, eventually (Oct 1956) published in Pegasus (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous printed material, 1959; 1961,; undated (Box 8)
    "Aviation in the Antarctic" by Henry M. Dater July 1959
    "Antarctic Photography" undated
    "Deep Freeze Communications" undated
    "How McMurdo Gets Its Water" undated
    "Rear Admiral David M. Tyree, USN Commander, U.S. Naval Support Force, Antarctica" May 1961
    "Some Cold Facts About the Antarctic" by Captain Edwin A. McDonald undated
    "USNS 'Eltanin' to Become Antarctic Research Ship" undated
    "What's in a Name" undated
    untitled, 2 items
- International Geophysical Year
  - Published material
    - Antarctic Program of the United States National Committee for the International Geophysical Year, Sept. 1957 (Box 8)
    - Antarctica in the International Geophysical Year, 1956 (Box 8)
    - "Nations Participating in the IGY (1957-1958)", Nov. 1954 (Box 8)
    - U. S. National Committee Report, United States National Committee for the International Geophysical Year, June 1954 (Box 8)
  - Reports
    - "International Geophysical Year", Sept. 2, 1955 (Box 8)
    - "U.S. Geological Survey Post-IGY Scientific Program, FY 59", Apr. 1958 (Box 8)
- U.S.S. Glacier
  - Gazette "News of All Sort" - vol. 2, no. 79, Jan. 7, 1957 (Box 8)
  - "Plan of the Day", Jan. 7-8, 1957 (Box 8)
- Antarctic Conference Preparations
  - Correspondence, July 1958-Apr. 1959; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Proposals for the management of the Antarctic programs, July 1959 (Box 8)
- Retirement
  - Alco Products, Inc. Nuclear power plant, George Dufek Day, Apr. 16, 1959 (Box 8)
  - Antarctic Commission, statements before the House, June 14, 1960 (Box 8)
  - Article, "New Skipper of the Mariners' Museum" by William Shands Meacham, The Commonwealth, May 1961 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1972; undated; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Journal, 1959; Dec. 1962 (Box 9)
  - Naval internal memos, Apr. 1959 (Box 9)
  - Press releases, Nov. 23, 1959 (Box 9)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - "Arctic Ice Breaker Operations," The Oni Review, summer 1948; Feb. 1949; includes draft (Box 9)
    - "Gold Discovered in Antarctica!", undated; holograph (Box 9)
    - "Operation Deepfreeze Nine Great Flights," Pegasus, Oct. 1956 (Box 9)
    - "Penguins and People", 1939 (Box 9)
    - "What We Accomplished in Antarctica," The National Geographic Magazine, Oct. 1959 (Box 9)
  - Biographical sketch of Rear Admiral Richard Evelyn Bird, Oct. 4, 1969 (Box 9)
  - Book, Great Polar Explorations, 1962; typescript draft (Box 9)
  - Galleys, Operation Deepfreeze, pp. 180-209, with corrections and insertions (Box 9)
  - Report to the Secretary of Defense, 1959 (Box 9)
  - Reviews
    - New Zealand in Color by John Pascoe, Daily Press, Newport News, Va. New Dominion Magazine, Jan. 24, 1970 (Box 9)
    - Remembrances of Rivers Past by Ernest Schwiebert, Apr. 1972; typescript (Box 9)
  - Speeches
    - "Lecture delivered to CNO Conference", Feb. 3, 1949 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1948; undated (Box 9)
- Memorabilia
  - Articles in Oriental script, undated; photocopies (Box 9)
  - Certificates (Box 9)
  - "Commendation of Dr. James Elliott Mooney", Mar. 2, 1966 (Box 9)
  - Czech music: The Little Kitten; The Last Day; The Bagpipes and the Contrabass, Supraphon F 09 01939, dufek_g_002; phonodisc, 45 rpm (Box 6)
    7" 45 rpm vinyl disc with a spindle hole for a turntable and perforations in the label to punch out a hole for a jukebox 45 rpm adapter. Label is in Czech with handwritten English translations for song titles on both sides. Resleeved and housed in poly bag. Folder of discs also contains a Czech customs declaration for "3 gramophone records" dated May 7, 1963.
  - Czech music: Old Czech Folk Songs, Supraphon F 05 10436, dufek_g_003; phonodisc, 45 rpm (Box 6)
    7" 45 rpm vinyl disc with a spindle hole for a turntable and perforations in the label to punch out a hole for a jukebox 45 rpm adapter. Label is in Czech with handwritten English description "Old Czech Folk Songs" on one side. Resleeved and housed in poly bag. Folder of discs also contains a Czech customs declaration for "3 gramophone records" dated May 7, 1963.
  - Czech music: The Little Sun; The Vain Cousin, Supraphon F 09 10983, dufek_g_004; phonodisc, 45 rpm (Box 6)
  - Interview with Dufek, Armed Forces Radio & Television Service, New York, N.Y., 04/14/1959; dufek_g_001; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
    Cut # 1: Change of Command Ceremony on board USS Glacier; Cut # 2: Interview with Rear Admiral Geroge [sic] Dufek by JOC H.E. Davis For Armed Forces Radio. Two tracking sheets enclosed in the tape box with the tape, one signed by JOC H.E. Davis for shipping to Rear Admiral George Dufek as a personal presentation copy. Back of the tape box labeled "Dateline NATO," "AFRS," dated 4-24-57 with a running time of 4:25 at 7.5 ips, but the front of the box has a round LP sticker labeled "Interview With Rear Admiral Geroge [sic] Dufek, April 14, 1959."
  - Invitations (Box 9)
  - Maps (Box 9)
  - Photographs, personal (Box 10)
  - Photographs, military, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Poetry, "McMurdo Lament or the Penguin Chorus", undated (Box 10)
  - Speech, "New Views of the Antarctic" by Finn Ronne, 1958 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous names, addresses, telephone numbers (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous notes for writings, speeches (Box 10)
  - Miscellany (Box 10)
  - Printed material
    - Articles about Antarctica, 1955-1960 (Box 10)
    - Clippings
      - Clippings, 1946; 1948,; 1949,; 1952,; 1955-1960; 11 folders (Box 10)
      - Clippings, 1961-1962; 1971,; undated; 5 folders (Box 10)
      - Deep Freeze scrapbook, The Press, 1957-1958 (Box 10)
      - Deep Freeze scrapbook, The Christchurch Star-Sun, 1957-1958 (Box 10)
      - Deep Freeze scrapbook, miscellaneous publications, 1958-1959; clippings (Box 10)
    - Resignation of Sir Anthony Eden, The Christchurch Star-Sun, Jan. 10, 1957 (Box 10)
    - Berlin Crisis, The New York Times, Nov. 1958 (Box 10)
    - Galleys, Polar Flight, by Ian Allan, undated (Box 10)
    - Magazines, miscellaneous, 3 items (Box 10)
    - Report, "Construction of the Army Nuclear Power Plant PM-2A at Camp Century, Greenland", final report, 1961 (Box 10)
    - Transactions, American Geophysical Union, Mar. 1959 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbooks
    See also Clippings: Deep Freeze scrapbook, The Press; Clippings: Deep Freeze scrapbook, The Christchurch Star-Sun; and Clippings: Deep Freeze scrapbook, miscellaneous publications, above
    - [Scrapbook #1], Aug-Oct. 1956 (Oversize 1)
    - [Scrapbook #2], Oct-Dec 1956 (Oversize 1)
    - [Scrapbook #3], Mar-July 1957 (Oversize 2)
    - [Scrapbook #4], Oct-Nov 1957 (Oversize 2)
    - [Scrapbook #5], Jun 1957-Dec 1958 (Oversize 3)
    - [Scrapbook #6], Nov 1957-Mar 1958 (Oversize 3)
    - [Scrapbook #7], Oct 1958 (Oversize 4)
    - [Scrapbook #8], Aug 1958-Jan 1959 (Oversize 4)
    - [Scrapbook #9] "The Story of the Deepfreeze as it Appeared Daily in the NYT", 1955-1956 (Oversize 5)
    - [Scrapbook #10] "vol. 3, Deepfreeze Adm. George Dufek", Dec 7, 1956-Jan 1957 (Oversize 5)
    - [Scrapbook #11] "Rear Adm. Dufek's Deepfreeze Scrapbook v. 4", Jan 15, 1957-Feb 23, 1957 (Oversize 6)
    - [Scrapbook #12] "Rear Adm. Dufek's Deep Freeze Scrapbook v. 5", Feb. 25, 1957-Mar. 26, 1957 (Oversize 6)
  - Wall plaque, "Admiral Byrd's Greatest Discovery" (Oversize 6)